<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on Liu</title>
    <link>http://localhost:44985/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on Liu</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:44985/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Academic research</title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/posts/academic-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/posts/academic-research/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I had a chat with friends about the importance of academic research.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We are in a revolutionizing era. Scientific advancements frequently appear in headlines. AI, robots, VR, a lot of them have already found applications in our daily life. Even rockets, as SpaceX envisions, will make space traveling as easy as taking a flight on the earth some day.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As a researcher myself, who also wants to contribute to the scientific world, I find my projects fall far behind the news headlines. When everybody talks about chatbots and image generations, my field of research seems not relevant and fading out.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Focusing prioritizing and being realistic</title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/posts/2021-12-01-focusing-prioritizing-and-being-realistic/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/posts/2021-12-01-focusing-prioritizing-and-being-realistic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How many things can I do a day?&#xA;I used to think I can read two papers in the morning.&#xA;In the mean time, I can prepare the experiment in the afternoon.&#xA;After the experiment, I can analyze all the data with my &amp;ldquo;miraculous&amp;rdquo; code with just a click.&#xA;I can even have fun in the evening!&#xA;It looks like, I can have such a &amp;ldquo;fruitful&amp;rdquo; day as a researcher, without spending much time.&#xA;However, this was just a daydream which I had from time to time in the past several years.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linux study notes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/posts/2021-01-01-linux-study-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/posts/2021-01-01-linux-study-notes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Linux has two main branches: &lt;strong&gt;Debian and RedHat&lt;/strong&gt;. Debian is meant for personal use, with a popular example Ubuntu. RedHat is meant for server use, with a popular example of CentOS. I&amp;rsquo;m going to learn the basics of servers, so the distro of interest here will be &lt;strong&gt;CentOS&lt;/strong&gt;. The reference of this note is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bilibili.com/video/BV1zL411T7YY&#34;&gt;this video course&lt;/a&gt;. This course is intent for server setup.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-virtual-machine&#34;&gt;I. Virtual Machine&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I used to think only when I have many computers can I test out a server. In fact, it only requires a virtual machine, or several virtual machines. I&amp;rsquo;ve already set up &lt;strong&gt;VMware&lt;/strong&gt; on my laptop.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy spectrum 2 methods</title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/posts/2020-11-11-energy-spectrum-2-methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/posts/2020-11-11-energy-spectrum-2-methods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have two methods for computing energy spectrum from spatial velocity data. In this post we should how they are related and point out quantitative details when converting between the results from these methods.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-two-methods&#34;&gt;1 Two methods&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;11-fftreal-real-part-of-standard-fft&#34;&gt;1.1 FFTreal: real part of standard fft&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Energy spectrum function $$E(k)$$ is defined as&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;$$&#xA;E(k) = \oint \frac{1}{2} \Phi_{ii}(k)d S(k)&#xA;$$&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;where $$\Phi_{ii}(k)$$ is the diagonal term of velocity spectrum tensor, defined as&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GNF evolution</title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/posts/2020-07-07-gnf-evolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/posts/2020-07-07-gnf-evolution/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Giant number fluctuation (GNF) is a key distinction of active matter compared to systems in equilibrium. Theories have predicted the deviation of number fluctuations in active matter in a quantitative way. Later on, the predictions are tested in experiment and were mostly true. Despite the success of the theories, the underlying mechanism of GNF still remains to be a hypothesis due to the difficulty of resolving individual active units and the interaction between individual active units in a crowded collection. A recent work by Peng et al. shows that in the transition to active turbulence, flow order and flow energy grow with different time scale. GNF also grows during the course of active turbulence transition, by look at the time scale of this transition, we could gain more insight into the mechanism of GNF.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/posts/01082022-french-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/posts/01082022-french-notes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;french-learning-notes&#34;&gt;French Learning Notes&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-pronunciation&#34;&gt;I. Pronunciation&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There is an international phonetic alphabet (IPA), which provides phonetic notations for every French words (and words in other languages too) using the same standard.&lt;/strong&gt; It&amp;rsquo;s similar to the English phonetic notations, except that it has some special ones that English does not have, e.g. /ʀ/ for letter &lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;. Note that /ʀ/ is smaller than the regular R. &lt;strong&gt;To learn the pronunciations of French words correctly in the beginning, I will learn each word together with their phonetic notations.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.collinsdictionary.com/dictionary/french-english&#34;&gt;Collins dictionary&lt;/a&gt; provides very good phonetic notation resources, as well as good explanations and examples. So look up words there when learning vocabulary.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/posts/2019-06-01-chiral-overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/posts/2019-06-01-chiral-overview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Chiral particles drift in shear flows because of their asymmetric shape. A simple case that helps to understand this drift is provided by Marcos et al. (PRL 2009) where a helical particle is aligned with a simple shear flow.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:44985/assets/images/2019/06/0.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;{:width=&amp;ldquo;300px&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The segments perpendicular to the flow direction have greater resistance than those parallel to the flow. Since the top (red) and bottom (black) halves experience different external flow velocity in a shear flow, there is a net force acting perpendicularly to the axis of the helical particle. In the case shown in the schematic above, the net force on the particle results in a drift to -z direction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/posts/2021-12-10-personal-server/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/posts/2021-12-10-personal-server/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since 2013, when I was an undergrad working on nanoparticle simulations, I was fascinated by sending the code to a server cluster to execute. The cluster was not faraway at all, like most servers in the world we are interacting with. Instead, they were just ~20 normal computers sitting in a small chamber in our office. They were running all day and all night and produce results silently.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;During my PhD at the University of Minnesota, this experience drove me to try out the Minnesota Supercomputing Institute (MSI), a much larger computing server that serves the whole university. Frankly speaking, MSI is no much different than the &amp;ldquo;next door&amp;rdquo; server I used before. After logging into the linux commandline, everything is so familiar. The only difference is I was not allowed to execute my code directly. Instead, I had to submit a job file to &amp;ldquo;queue&amp;rdquo; my commands, and the system will decide when my code are executed. I understand that for a server of this scale (for 10,000s people), this &amp;ldquo;queue&amp;rdquo; mechanism makes the system more stable.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/posts/2021-12-30-mendeley-to-zotero/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/posts/2021-12-30-mendeley-to-zotero/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I quit Mendeley today, after 5 years of use, because there are serious problems with duplicated files, lack of support for mobile platforms, small cloud drive and poor syncing quality. Solving these problems has been distracting me from focusing on reading, so that I decide to try out some alternatives and leave Mendeley.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After reviewing many alternatives I decided to try &lt;strong&gt;Zotero&lt;/strong&gt;, an open-source software that should be able to connect with google drive, so I don&amp;rsquo;t have to pay for cloud storage one more time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/posts/2021-12-30-mold-on-wall/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/posts/2021-12-30-mold-on-wall/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here are some pictures of the apartment at 24 Boulevard Arago Paris 75013 during our stay, mainly taken in November and December 2021. The pictures show that there was a large fraction of wall surface covered by green and black mold colonies, likely caused by high humidity. We open all the windows for about 8 hours in the day, despite the cold weather in November, and use extra electricity to heat up the chamber, the mold problem persisted. We suspect that the apartment we stayed was not properly moisture proofed. Consequently, the walls of the apartment (at least the wall paper) were damaged and the apartment was humid, cold and had unpleasant smells, hence not suitable for accommodate people.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/posts/2023-02-09-jekyll/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/posts/2023-02-09-jekyll/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I start to reorganize my personal website with &lt;a href=&#34;https://jekyllrb.com/&#34;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;. I knew this tool from the first day I tried GitHub Pages (perhaps in 2018). At that time, I did not read through the documentation and thought this is only a &amp;ldquo;theme&amp;rdquo; tool, which modifies my website to a look I don&amp;rsquo;t like. So I did not use it, but started from scratch to build an HTML + CSS static site. It was a happy learning process. I started to learn using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://freecodecamp.org&#34;&gt;freecodecamp online app&lt;/a&gt;, and got good understanding of the web development basics. With some practice, I eventually was able to tune my website front page to the way I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/posts/2023-02-13-my-competencies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/posts/2023-02-13-my-competencies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While searching for a job, I find it useful to outline my competencies and weaknesses, so that I can quickly compare with the qualifications of the jobs and assess my fit. The content of this post would be very much aligned with a cover letter of a job application. Hence, it could be reused in the near future!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I got my batchelor&amp;rsquo;s degree from the Polymer Material and Engineering Department at Tsinghua University. In an undergraduate research training program, I took on a computational study of a nanoparticle system which is responsive to external mechanical stimuli. Despite of the short time, this training left me with great values: (i) curiosity for scientific research, (ii) solid coding skills.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to construct pandas DataFrame efficiently</title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/posts/2023-03-09-construct-dataframe/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/posts/2023-03-09-construct-dataframe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, I was reviewing my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ZLoverty/DE/blob/main/Code/HoughCircles-DE.ipynb&#34;&gt;droplet tracking code&lt;/a&gt; and saw an interesting way to construct &lt;code&gt;pandas.DataFrame&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Construct a list of DataFrame, each representing a row: &lt;code&gt;row_list = [pd.DataFrame({&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;: i, &amp;quot;b&amp;quot;: 2*i} for i in range(100))]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Concatenate the list into a bigger DataFrame: &lt;code&gt;df = pd.concat(row_list)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is not what I normally do, and that&amp;rsquo;s probably why I find it interesting. Normally, I would&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;populate two lists for &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;code&gt;a_list = [i for i in range(100)]; b_list = [2*i for i in range(100)]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;use the lists to initiate DataFrame: &lt;code&gt;df = pd.DataFrame({&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;: a_list, &amp;quot;b&amp;quot;: b_list})&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Intuitively, the second way is faster, because it involves less DataFrame construction. But I do like the first way, in that I do not have to initiate many temporary lists. So I Google it and find &lt;a href=&#34;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/17091769/python-pandas-fill-a-dataframe-row-by-row&#34;&gt;this question&lt;/a&gt;, which gives another intuitive way to do this:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pigment and structural color</title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/posts/2024-05-23-pigment-and-structural-color/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/posts/2024-05-23-pigment-and-structural-color/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today when I listened to the podcast about “blueberry is not blue”, I recalled the question I heard a few years ago “what is the difference between colloid color and dye color”. Even to this day, I still don’t have a solid understanding of the physics of color, but rather some scattered pieces of knowledge with terminologies that do not necessarily make sense, such as Rayleigh scattering and absorption by chemical bonds. But the question is still there: is there a unified framework to understand color?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Principle Componenets Analysis</title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/posts/2023-03-10-principle-component-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/posts/2023-03-10-principle-component-analysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have tried to learn machine learning a few times. However, I never find the chance to implement any machine learning algorithm in my research. Here, I want to revisit the subject by reading Goodfellow&amp;rsquo;s book. I like simple things, because they help me understand the basic concept and gain intuition to the abstract math. Principle componenets analysis is such a simple thing, which I shall take some notes here to try to understand.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Youtube audio prep</title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/posts/2024-12-27-youtube-audio-prep/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/posts/2024-12-27-youtube-audio-prep/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I got interested in listening to history lectures on Youtube. Since many of the lectures are long and the video part is usually unimportant, I start to conceive a more portable format of lecture, which is ad-free and does not require Internet access. This leads to the idea of downloading the videos and converting them to audios came up.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;batch-download&#34;&gt;Batch download&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I started with websites like &lt;em&gt;y2mate&lt;/em&gt;. They worked, but when I want to download a series of videos, they are not satisfactory because I have to wait for the first one to complete before starting the second one. Ideally, I should be able to make a list of videos I want to download and to have a software keep downloading according to the list &amp;ndash; to enable batch download.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>中文日志</title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/posts/2023-03-05-%E4%B8%AD%E6%96%87%E6%97%A5%E5%BF%97/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/posts/2023-03-05-%E4%B8%AD%E6%96%87%E6%97%A5%E5%BF%97/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;这是我在这个网站上写的第一篇中文日志。&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;说起我写日志，最早可以追溯到高中时期的 QQ 空间。当时临近高考，似乎是人生中第一次感受到压力，却又不想让太多人分担压力，便开始以文字为倾诉对象。到了大学，我慢慢放弃了 QQ 空间，一是因为它不再流行，二是因为有些日志更为隐私不愿公开，所以开始用纸笔记录生活和思考。在美国读博士期间，不知是不是生活压力小了，五年时间也没有再写几篇，如今想来还是比较遗憾。直到临近毕业，又感受到压力时，才有了倾诉的冲动，在 iPad 上写下寥寥几笔。来到法国之后，由于[在租公寓上踩了大坑]({% post_url 2021-12-30-Mold-on-wall %})，以及遇到了居留许可、医保等等问题，我又重拾日志开始倾诉。当时由于需要频繁插图，所以没有手写，而是用 &lt;a href=&#34;https://obsidian.md/&#34;&gt;Obsidian&lt;/a&gt;，一个 markdown 笔记软件。当时我已经开始在 GitHub 上用 markdown 笔记记录研究进展几个月，不愿意用 GitHub 写日志是想把工作和生活分开。从 2021 年年底至今，那篇 Obsidian 里题为“在法国工作生活中的一些问题”的日志已经更新了十次有余，记录了痛苦的找房过程，难忘的坐船经历，以及第一次感染新冠的体验。虽然我记事多是波澜不惊的流水账，但如今再读，还是有些感触，也觉得那些文字对自己颇为珍贵。&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;最近偶然读到&lt;a href=&#34;https://yihui.org/&#34;&gt;谢益辉&lt;/a&gt;的博客，看到一些有共鸣的观点。最突出的一条出自&lt;a href=&#34;https://yihui.org/cn/2020/07/silence/&#34;&gt;万言万当，不如一默&lt;/a&gt;：&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;最后，我大学本科读到过一首诗，里面有一句“跳舞吧，像没有人会欣赏一样”。年少时读它，觉得它的意旨是鼓励人们勇敢追求。现在读它，觉得是在劝人把生活的重心从外移到内，逐渐学会不假外求、反求诸己。所以“写日志吧，就像没有人会阅读一样”。于是现在我写日志时，都倾向于写给自己看，只有少数时候应和一下其它博主或读者。等它们发布出来时，我自己可能已经读了百十来遍了。&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;我不善于在他人面前展现自我，不论是真实的自我，还是我想维持的人设。现实中，我是个孤独的人，或许在别人眼中是个怪人。我抗拒微博、朋友圈等社交网络，用微信也是为了联系家人朋友，看到别人的动态或多或少心烦，一方面看到同龄人过得比我好而感到压力，另一方面又会觉得别人过得好坏与我何干。所以我也不分享自己的动态，因为我做什么与绝大多数人，也毫不相干。但是，我也常常有记录生活的冲动和需要，所以我选择写日志，之所以发在网上，是因为我也时不时回看自己以前写的东西，而写在网上就方便我随时随地回看。&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;刚出国时有些文化自卑，很少在公开网络上写中文内容，但最近读了一些中文博客，感觉中文毕竟是母语，读写起来都更有味道，所以决定同时维护一个中文日志。或许以后会搬运一些写在别处的老日志，也会写些新的，希望多年以后，这些日志能在喧闹的世界中为我创造一片安宁。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
