<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Research on Liu</title>
    <link>http://localhost:44985/research/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Research on Liu</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:44985/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Active nematics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/research/active_nematics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/research/active_nematics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We study active nematics under confinement.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active turbulence</title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/research/turbulence/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/research/turbulence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Active turbulence refers to the turbulent-like flows induced by a large number of self-propelling agents, such as bacteria. Although such phenomenon has been discovered for serveral decades, the process of the transition to turbulence is not well characterized. In this work, we measured the evolution of both the flow order and mean flow velocity, and identified two kinetic pathways. Which pathway a system chooses depends on the concentration of bacteria.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beet fringe</title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/research/beet_fringe/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/research/beet_fringe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We study the cause of the fringe formation around a beet slice when it&amp;rsquo;s put on a thin liquid film.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bubble cleaning</title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/research/bubble_cleaning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/research/bubble_cleaning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We aim to develop a novel, environmental friendly technique for cleaning fresh produce.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Condensation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/research/condensation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/research/condensation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We study the condensation vapor flux around a porous material, such as a fungal colony.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Double emulsions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/research/double_emulsion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/research/double_emulsion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The interplay between complex environments and active matter suggests a possibility to control and engineer active matter by carefully designing the confinement structures.&#xA;It is now well established that confinement may influence transport, rheology, pressure, spatial distribution and collective motion of active matter.&#xA;Curved confining walls, which are ubiquitous in biological systems, show their own, specific rich and intriguing effects on active matter.&#xA;Here, using a double emulsion system, where the inner and outer droplet sizes can be independently controlled, we experimentally investigate the influence of curved confinement on an active bath of &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; bacteria.&#xA;In particular, we analyze the fluctuations of the inner droplet using the framework of a stochastic &amp;ldquo;active noise&amp;rdquo; model, and show that the strength of active noise is not an intrinsic property of an active bath, but depends on the confinement curvature.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drying crack of bacterial droplets</title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/research/crack/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/research/crack/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Particulate suspensions form cracks when desicated. This is a very ubiquitous phenomenon, with examples ranging from mud cracks in a dried river bed to a dried blood droplet. The mechanism behind this phenomenon is usually the same: the top layer of the drying suspension lose suspending liquid and tend to contract, while the bottom material stays the same size. However, the resulting crack patterns can be very different for different materials. Understanding crack patterns has potential applications, for example in blood diagnostics. We find an interesting and aesthetically pleasing crack pattern formed by drying &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; suspensions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Giant number fluctuations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/research/gnf/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/research/gnf/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Giant number fluctuations (GNF) is one of the key differences between active systems and equilibrium systems, characterized by the number fluctuations scaling with system size. I experimentally investigate the number fluctuations in 3D bacterial suspensions, and its correlation with the flow field. We find an interesting correspondence between number fluctuations and energy spectra, which is scale-invariant and concentration-independent.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;related-stuff&#34;&gt;Related stuff&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:44985/presentations/DFD2020.pdf&#34;&gt;DFD 2020 slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Porous media</title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/research/porous_media/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/research/porous_media/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Bacteria are microswimmers commonly found in complex environments, such as substrate surface, porous media and external flows. How they adapt to these environments is not only crucial to their suvival, but also important for the biological processes they are involved in, such as biofilm formation and infection. Due to the ecological and medical relevance of bacterial motility in complex environments, it has been investigated in more detail, thanks to the development of fast video microscopy. Here, we study the motility of the model microswimmer &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; near glass surface, in the presence of a layer of oil droplets (3 um and 10 um in diameter). This droplet system simulates a soft tissue surface, while permitting direct and simultaneous imaging of both bacteria and obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rheology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:44985/research/rheology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:44985/research/rheology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is my first research project in my PhD program at Minnesota, studying the confinement effect on the rheology of bacterial suspensions. Back then, I did not have the habit of writing notes and blogs for specific problems or findings, so there is not many records of how the project evolved over time. However, there are slides and posters I made back then on this project, which hopefully provide a good overview.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
